<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: startup | Shawn Dahlen]]></title>
  <link href="http://smdahlen.github.com/blog/categories/startup/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://smdahlen.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-13T17:31:36-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://smdahlen.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Shawn Dahlen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prepare business operations]]></title>
    <link href="http://smdahlen.github.com/blog/2013/03/05/prepare-business-operations/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-05T13:41:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://smdahlen.github.com/blog/2013/03/05/prepare-business-operations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With my <a href="http://shawn.dahlen.me/blog/2013/02/25/shifting-my-attention/">attention</a>
now focused on the startup, I spent this week bootstrapping the business. The
objective was to establish a project plan achievable within thirty weeks while
preparing technical and financial operations. Before I dive into the
particulars of the schedule, let me provide a look into what I will be working on.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Product</h2>

<p>Before I made the leap, I had several ideas worth pursuing. Most were mid to large
in size. I would have had to create a working prototype over the thirty week
time period and raise venture capital to take it to the next step. Instead, I
decided to focus on a niche and implement a full solution within the same timeframe
with the mid-term objective of generating semi-passive income that could seed
bigger ideas.</p>

<p>The niche I will be targeting is a task management app that provides first-class
support for the <a href="http://www.pomodorotechnique.com/">Pomodoro Technique</a>. Why you ask? First and foremost, it scratches my own itch. As Paul Graham penned in
<a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/startupideas.html">How To Get Startup Ideas</a>, the best
ideas are ones in which the founders themselves want and can build. While
there exists many first-class task management solutions, none provide rich support
for arguably one of the most <a href="http://lifehacker.com/5890129/five-best-productivity-methods">popular productivity methods</a>. I will initially launch with a web-based
interface and follow with iOS and Android versions pending traction of the
product. More information will follow regarding the product, its features, and
user experience in several weeks.</p>

<h2>The Plan</h2>

<p>The plan is simple. I have divided the thirty weeks into five sprints each
with a specific work package (objective). The work package is further decomposed
into six tasks that are approximately one week of effort each. This approach
afforded me a clear weekly focus that I could subsequently share with you.</p>

<p>I opted to tackle the product architecture first versus the typical approach of
defining product requirements. I felt that more risk existed with the product
architecture since I had not operated systems on the Internet before while the
base requirements are already well-defined within the Pomodoro Technique
<a href="http://www.pomodorotechnique.com/download/pdf/ThePomodoroTechnique_v1-3.pdf">book</a>.</p>

<p>With the current plan, I intend to launch the product in early October (accounting
for some vacation time with my family).</p>

<p><strong>Sprints</strong></p>

<ol>
<li>Define and prototype the product architecture

<ul>
<li>Week 1: Automate provisioning of secure servers</li>
<li>Week 2: Setup Node.js servers within a load-balanced configuration</li>
<li>Week 3: Setup a MongoDb database cluster</li>
<li>Week 4: Setup an automated functional testing framework</li>
<li>Week 5: Setup a performance testing framework</li>
<li>Week 6: Setup a monitoring and backup strategy</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Define product user experience

<ul>
<li>Week 7: Draft personas, goals, and feature requirements</li>
<li>Week 8: Draft paper storyboards</li>
<li>Week 9: Establish a visual design</li>
<li>Week 10: Draft design compositions for time and inventory features</li>
<li>Week 11: Draft design compositions for reporting and gameplay features</li>
<li>Week 12: Draft design compositions for registration and payment features</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Implement registration, time, and inventory features</li>
<li>Implement reporting, gameplay, and payment features</li>
<li>Conduct testing and draft marketing plan</li>
</ol>


<h2>Other Activities</h2>

<p>Beyond defining the schedule and the associated research required to scope it, I
tackled a few other activities in preparation for week one kickoff:</p>

<ul>
<li>I incorporated my business, tenatively named <em>Whimsical Bits, Ltd.</em>, through
<a href="http://www.rocketlawyer.com/">Rocket Lawyer</a> and drafted my LLC Operating
Agreement.</li>
<li>I implemented a <a href="https://github.com/smdahlen/mac-bootstrap">script</a> to bootstrap
my mac for software development that includes setup of homebrew, vim, irssi,
rbenv, and a few ruby gems (which I will discuss next week). Additionally, I
refined my personal <a href="https://github.com/smdahlen/dotfiles">dotfiles</a> that
intend to push to all servers I work on.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
